<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A manifest and apparent confutation of an astrological discourse, lately published to the discomfort (without cause) of the weake and simple sort, as will by the sequel of that which foloweth, euidently appeare With a briefe prognostication, or astrologicall prediction, of the coniunction of the two superiour planets, Saturn and Iupiter: which shalbe in the year of our Lord God 1583 the 29. of Aprill, at three of the clocke in the morning. / VVritten the 25. of March by Thomas Heth, Master of Art.</title>
            <author>Heath, Thomas, astronomer.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13255.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841827</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841827</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6440</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6440)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 345:9 or 1960:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A manifest and apparent confutation of an astrological discourse, lately published to the discomfort (without cause) of the weake and simple sort, as will by the sequel of that which foloweth, euidently appeare With a briefe prognostication, or astrologicall prediction, of the coniunction of the two superiour planets, Saturn and Iupiter: which shalbe in the year of our Lord God 1583 the 29. of Aprill, at three of the clocke in the morning. / VVritten the 25. of March by Thomas Heth, Master of Art.</title>
                  <author>Heath, Thomas, astronomer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[84] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, dwelling in Foster Lane, ouer against Gold-smiths Hal, at the signe of the George. By the assent of Richard VVatkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1583]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Harvey, Richard.  An astrological discourse upon the great and notable conjunction of the two superiour planets, Saturne &amp; Jupiter, which shall happen the 28. day of April, 1583.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A] B-E F2.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>This edition has B1r catchword: Lastly,.</note>
                  <note>Quire [A] and B1r are reimposed from STC 13255.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 13255 on UMI microfilm reel 345.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 345 and at reel 1960 (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harvey, Richard, 1560-1623? --  Astrological discourse upon the great and notable conjunction of the two superiour planets, Saturne &amp; Jupiter, which shall happen the 28. day of April, 1583.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:1"/>
            <p>¶ A manifeſt and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <hi>confutation of an Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>diſcourſe, lately publiſhed to</hi> the diſcomfort (without cauſe) of the</hi> weake and ſimple ſort, as will by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel <hi>of that which followeth, eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a briefe Prognoſtication, or Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall <hi>prediction, of the coniunction of the two Superiour planets,</hi>
               </hi> Saturn <hi>and</hi> Iupiter: <hi>which ſhalbe in the year of our Lord God</hi> 1583 <hi>the</hi> 29. <hi>of Aprill, at three of the clocke in the morning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVritten the 25. of March by THOMAS HETH, Maſter of Art.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>GOD IS MY DEFENDER.</head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by <hi>Robert Walde-graue,</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> in Foſter Lane, ouer againſt Gold-ſmiths Hal, at the ſigne of the George.</p>
            <p>By the aſſent of RICHARD VVATKINS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE READER, IT may ſeeme a thing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then needful to write of that, whereof ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath vvritten ſo lately, yea and as the moſt thinke, ſo largely and learnedly, as is poſſible in that behalfe, and nothing omitted therein that might any way tend to the declaration ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. The conſideration vvhereof cauſed mee at the firſt to pauſe at the matter, and in ſo doing, found them that had hitherto vvritten thereof, to haue miſtaken the grounde of all their iudgement, preſuppoſing a vvrong and vntrue time of the coniunction of the ſaide Planets, wherevpon they ſeeme to grounde the principles of al their iudgements, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I could not but certifie you thereof, and with the beſt of my endeuour, ſeeking to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you with the trueth, haue enterpriſed to write this treatiſe following, in humble wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:6440:3"/> praying you well to accept the plaineſſe and ſimpleneſſe of the ſtile, as of one, not ſo well exerciſed in the eloquent pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning or the retho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rical flouriſhing of any peece of work (though the ſame be a thing very commendable and requiſite) as in the contemplacion and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the art, cheefeſt to be expected herein, hoping that no indifferent perſon vvill thinke the worſe of ſo excellent a ſcience, for that the ſtudents in the ſame profeſſion, ſeeme to vvrite the one directly contrary to the other: the firſt, threatning great harme to the vvhol world, the ſecond, promiſing good hap to the ſame, the rather, becauſe that contrariety in writing, is a thing not onely incident to this profeſſion, but alſo vnto ſundry other ſtudies vvherin the learned in ech faculty are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and iudge; who in his profeſſion vvri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth moſt learnedly and ſubſtantially, vnto vvhoſe cenſure I ſubmit my ſelfe, and this my trauell, vviſhing that as well the vnskilfull A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomer, vvhich takes vppon him the Art vvithout knowledge thereof, making moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of Molhills, and myracles of meere tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, might be better aduiſed ere hee publiſh his doings to the vievv of the vvorld, diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting himſelfe and the Art thereby, as alſo that the vnlearned &amp; ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſort, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuriouſly vpbraid and defame the ſame, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough their diſpightfull and malicious ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches (for that the predictions which the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfull
<pb facs="tcp:6440:3"/> in this ſcience prognoſticat, anſwere not their expectation to the full, either to ſuſpend their iudgements (for that the blinde are not able to iudge or diſcerne colours) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther els to impute the fault, where of right it ought, vnto the artiſt and not vnto the Art VVhich doing, their credite vvoulde be the more, and the commendation of the Art no leſſe then in truth it doth deſerue; and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vviſe their raſh and indiſcreet iudgement, wil no leſſe appeare herein, then in the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the common lawes without cauſe, when as their humour is not pleaſed, and their cauſe iuſtly condemned. But the Godly and learned through their example admoniſhed, whoſe iudgement is more, and meaning bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, will I hope well conceiue of my ſimple &amp; plaine meaning herein, to whoſe good conſideration I referre the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of that which followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>VVORSHIPFVLL</hi> Sir George Carey, <hi>Knight, and Knight</hi> MARSHALL OF HER MAIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties <hi>most Honorable houſhold:</hi> THOMAS HETH vviſheth long life vvith much fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight worſhipful, according to my duety vnto your worſhip, and my natiue Country, (though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what preuented by the haſty and raſhe atemptes of other ſome). I haue at this preſent
<pb facs="tcp:6440:5"/> publiſhed that, whereof I hope your worſhip will accept, which is my cenſure and opinion (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the groundes of Art) of the coniunction of the two ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Planettes, hapning in this yeare of our Lord, a thouſand fiue hundred eightie three, the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie eight day of Aprill, about the fifteenth houre of the Aſtronomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call daye. The which reduced to our vulgar accountp, is the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ninth day, at three of the clocke in the morning, or neare about the ſame, as I am able to prooue by plaine Demonſtration, though <hi>Leouitius</hi> and an imitatour of him, <hi>Frauncis Liberati,</hi> an Italian Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>Vir equidem ab omni liberatus iudicio,</hi> affirme the ſame to be the ſecond day of May, at three of the clocke, fifteene Minutes in the morning, vnder ſuche a Celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Scheme as followeth, erected for the Meridian of <hi>Paris.</hi> But howe farre hee erreth from the
<pb facs="tcp:6440:5"/> truth, the thing it ſelfe wil ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhew.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Stadius</hi> ſomewhat nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the truth, though farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, putteth it the twentie eight
<pb facs="tcp:6440:6"/> day of Aprill, iuſt at noone to them of <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> vnder ſuch a figure as followeth.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>The ſame by ſome reduced to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> very ſleightly. Wherfore before I can come to ſay any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I am driuen to diſprooue many
<pb facs="tcp:6440:6"/> of their miſtaken <hi>Axiomes.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſeem to bring the world into ſuch admiration, that they of the better ſort, knowe not what to thinke thereof, and the reſt more ſimple, brought into no ſmall feare and diſcomfort therby. As touching the firſt, who yeeldeth no reſon of his predictions, I boldly ſay, they are meere immaginary and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether friuolous. For if he iudge by the coniunction, he ſeemeth to leap ouer the ſtile before hee come at it. For that a great Coniunction, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe, Comet, or Reuolution can not worke any matter that ſhoulde come to effect before the ſame firſt appeare vnto the world, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were it, ſo that his eſtimate of the Coniunction were anye thing neere vnto the trueth, yet he coulde not prognoſticate therby anything to fall out before the time of the ſayd Coniunction (the ſame being the efficient occaſion thereof) as he doth in the beginning of this yeare
<pb facs="tcp:6440:7"/> 
               <hi>1583.</hi> the <hi>26.</hi> day of February two moneths before the coniunction, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges a greate manye of other ſtrange matters. His wordes bee theſe <hi>preparation de guerre en Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre &amp;c. non obstant les iours qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſme.</hi> Likewiſe the thirteenth day of March <hi>Diuiſion in Angliteire cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riers en Flanders &amp; en Almaygne. &amp;c</hi> Which ſaying becauſe it touched our natiue Country. I thought good to recite as alſo for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> (God be prayſed therefore) it came nothing ſo to paſſe. Nor nothing neere the trueth, for as all men know there was no cauſe of preparation to warre or likelihood thereof: much leſſe any preparation at all. But it is an ancient ſaying, and not ſo old as true, written by <hi>Ptholomi</hi> in his <hi>Cen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iloquio propoſitione <hi>12.</hi> Amor odiumque ne vera eueniant iudicia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibent, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quidem minuunt maxima, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent minima:</hi> and therefore my truſt and confidence is, that the reſt of his predictions, wherewith hee
<pb facs="tcp:6440:7"/> threatneth vs ſhall hurte vs no more then the former hath hyther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to done. <hi>Si deus enim nobiſcum quis contra nos,</hi> if God bee on cure ſide, who can be againſt vs. Agayne, if he had iudged by the reuolution (as it ſhould rather ſeeme he did) wher he putteth the ingreſſe of the ſunne into the firſt minute of <hi>Aries,</hi> to bee the tenth daye of Marche at <hi>8.</hi> a clock thirty two minutes at night, The twentie eight degree of <hi>Libra</hi> aſcending, and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Cancer</hi> in the ninth houſe, if that poſition had been true, as it is nothing ſo, yet <hi>Mars</hi> can not be Lord of the yeare by any reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aſtrologicall, being neither ſtrong in himſelfe, nor wel placed in the figure, for he is both in his fall, and in a cadent houſe, farre vnfit for that function, after the mind of any learned wryter in this ſcience. And yet this is his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. <hi>Mars plus puiſſant en la figure &amp; lieu de ciel, de tous les autres Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets ſera ſeigneur &amp; le diſpoſiteur de
<pb facs="tcp:6440:8"/> le an <hi>1583.</hi>
               </hi> And therefore with very good reaſon I conclude againſt him with the ſaying of <hi>Schoner, uomodo e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iahit Astrologus errorem, ſi capue anni (radicem predictionis ſuae) prorſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ignorauerit.</hi> That is to ſay how ſhal the Aſtrologer auoyd an errour in iudgement, if he be vtterly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the true beginning of the yeare the very ground of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
            <p>And now to returne to the other, who ſeemeth to write more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly and more amply of the ſame matter, though not vppon the ſame ground. Wherein verily he ſhewes him ſelfe a toward ſcholler, though not ſo perfect an Aſtrologer, in that hee leaneth ſomewhat too muche, (without cauſe) to the workes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wryters, as ſhall be declared hereafter, not examining whether there hath beene any errour or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight committed, either by the author or printer of the ſame. For in one of them there muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb facs="tcp:6440:8"/> ſome negligence appeare As for example <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eouitius,</hi> who was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently well learned, and daylie exerciſed in the Mathematicals, putteth the coniunction to bee the ſecond day of May, at thre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock in the morning? Who as it is well known, followed the <hi>Alphonſine</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, which at this day &amp; long ſince is founde (by the beſt learned) to halt, &amp; prooued inſufficient, exactly to account any apparent motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by. Wherfore no doubt (if he were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at this preſent) he would not let, (after proofe made) to ſay with otherſom, <hi>Errare po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um bereticus eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenolo.</hi> And <hi>Stadius</hi> of like credite, and no leſſe experience then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, affirmeth it to be the twenty eight day of April exactly at noone, vnder the conſtitution that goeth before, which is more then foure dayes different, and therefore muſt needes breede greate alteration in iudgement.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:9"/>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Moestlin</hi> who endeuoreſh himſelfe to winne no leſſe accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tton and credit then the reſt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is no doubt but he will if he perſeuer, (as he hath already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun) putteth it to be the ſame day, but ſixteene houres from noone, or at foure of the clocke the next day in the morning, and neareſt to the truth for certain. And though theſe writers do wryte for ſundry meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, as <hi>Augusta, Antwerpe,</hi> and <hi>Tubing,</hi> yet can not any reduction bring them all to be vnited or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable to any one of the ſaid thrée Cities, or any other meridian els, that one may ſafely ſay, this is the true houre and minute of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction. For neither <hi>Stadius</hi> (if he had beene willed) or <hi>Moestlin</hi> (if he ſhould be required) to put it downe to the view of the worlde, woulde truſt to his own <hi>Ephemerides,</hi> much leſſe to anye others, but rather woulde vouchſafe the ſupputation of the ſame out of the grounds ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.
<pb facs="tcp:6440:9"/> For although et be thought ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, in the ſupputation of an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemerides</hi> to come, within a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, two, or three of the true place of the Plar et at noone, yet is it to be otherwiſe requyred in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. For not onely to know the degree and minute is requyſite herein, but alſo the ſecond, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayde coniunction ſhall at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time happen. For as much as they may be both conioyned togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one degree, and ſame mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, the ſpace of fiue houres at leaſt, before the true coniunction, or no leſſe tyme after the ſame, throgh the ſlowneſſe of their motions. All which conſidered, I haue here ſet downe according to my ſimple ſkill, the figure thereof, ſo neere the truth as I poſſibly coulde. Which though I dare not warrant the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act minute of time, yet of the hour, I am well aſſured that no way I am deceiued, for as much as it hath bin ſupputated out of the grounds,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:10"/> eſteeming the ſame to bee with vs at <hi>London,</hi> the twentie ninth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> at three a clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, vnder ſuch a poſition as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>THis coniunction hapneth in the fift minute of the <hi>22.</hi> degree of
<pb facs="tcp:6440:10"/> 
               <hi>Piſces,</hi> the laſt ſigne of the <hi>zodiacke,</hi> and in the latter part of the twelfe houſe, which is termed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mers. <hi>Domus tristitiae, laboris, aerum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, maeroris, inimicitiarum, inuidiae, ſuſurrationis, carceris, ſeruorum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptorum, animalium magnorum. &amp;c.</hi> And whether it ought to ſeeme ſo fearefull and terrible vnto vs, as it is thought by ſome, we are to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine. And for aſmuch as it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the very beſt and worſt of all the Planets: we ought well to conſider, whether <hi>Saturne</hi> in his mallice and miſchiefe, be able and of ſufficient power to ſubdue the influence of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and thoſe good haps by him ſignified. And in as much as they twain, are not all in all, hauing to doe wholly in all cauſes, it is therefore requiſite and needfull, ioyntly io conſider with them, the Dominion and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the reſt in order, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:6440:11"/>
               <label>♄ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FORTITVDINES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Liber directus, velox, orientalis, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus lumine &amp; numero, receptus a io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue in domum, coniunctus loui, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo gaudij, in quarta conformi, in gra du lucido.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DEBILITATES.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peregrinus, in 12, deſc. in eccent, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picicio, &amp; in meridiem, in gradu va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuo &amp; in contrarietate haiz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <label>♃ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Directus, velox, auctus lumine &amp; nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero in domo propria, in conformi quarta, gradu lucido, coniunctus cum ſtella fixa de natura fortunae, orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis, liber.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſc. in epiciclo, eccentrico, &amp; in meridiem, coniunctus ſaturno, in 12. in gradu vacuo, in contrarietate haiz.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <label>♂ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Directus, aſc. in epici, &amp; ecce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitate ſexus &amp; quartae, in gradu auge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te fortunam, liber a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>buſtione. Tardus, minutus lumine &amp; numero peregrinus, in ſexta, in contrarietate haiz occidentalis.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>☉ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aſc. in eccent auctus numero, in ſuo haiz, in conformi quarta, in lextili io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, in horoſcopo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tardus, peregimus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6440:11"/>♀ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Directa, velox, aſc. in eccent, aucta lumine &amp; numero, occidentalis, in 2. domo, in conformi quarta, gradu lucido, lib. a combuſtione.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſc. in epici, in contrarietate haiz, peregrina.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <label>☿ <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Liber, directus, velox, aſc. in epici, in horoſcopo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Deſc in eccent, &amp; in metid, perigri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, in gradu vacuo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                  <hi>eſt</hi>
               </label>
               <item>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra a combuſ. in facie propria, recepta, in ſuo haiz, in conformi quarta, gradu lucido &amp; augente for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tarda, deſc. in epici, &amp; eccent, minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta lumine &amp; numero, in 8. domo, in quadrato ſaturni.</hi>
                  </p>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And now to come to the purpoſe, theſe former conſiderations wayd, if we compare the fortituds of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> with his debilities, we ſhall then find that he is ſtrong <hi>(propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſeſquialtera)</hi> his ſtrengths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aboue thirtie, his debilities, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>20.</hi> wherefore I may ſafely ſay, he is well affected, well ſituat, and very well configurate: no leſſe may he thought of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> though not
<pb facs="tcp:6440:12"/> hauing the ſame fortitudes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities in all pointes, yet the like in number, and ſame proportion, and are both as witneſſeth <hi>Cardan. In primo &amp; optimo statu, robustiſſimi, quia orientales, veloces &amp; aparentes.</hi> 
               <q>Wherefore it were very groſſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhold be ſo hatefull ſo hurtful, ſo diſpitefull, or ſo mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious by his force and authority, to ouercome and ſubdue the good nature, the ſweete influence, and proſperous irradiation of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolent and friendly Planet <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </q> Vpon his trial, who is found in all reſpectes to be as ſtrong, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as manlike, and as mighty as himſelfe, and hauing him at home in his owne houſe, hee may either entreate him as a friend, or elſe <hi>(de iure)</hi> commaunde him as a gueſt to be ruled, and be of good behauiour, yeelding the ſuperiority vnto his Hoſt, without cauſing great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of waters, cold weather, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted miſchiefes, ſorrow, enuie,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:12"/> debate, quarrelling, hate, ſtrife, lawing for the goods of the deade, reconinges, accountes, or ſuch like, the rather becauſe hee is neither in the eight, neither hath any domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion therein, nor beholdeth <hi>Mars</hi> the Lorde of the cuſpe of the ſame: for <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Piſces</hi> no way beholde the one the other. And whereas he threatneth thorow the influence of <hi>Saturne,</hi> vprores, tumultes, many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde troubles, violence and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he greatly miſtaketh the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for that they are rather the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the outragious, fell, and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Planet <hi>Mars,</hi> who in the coniunction hath little or nothing to doe. But if therevpon hee had threatned hunger, want, penurie, and pouertie vnto the poore and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent, his prediction had not been vnlike to haue taken effect, for that their eſtate is neuer better, and why he ſhould diſcomfort the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie or Eccleſiaſticall eſtate, I ſée no cauſe conſidering that <hi>Iupiter</hi> their
<pb facs="tcp:6440:13"/> generall ſignificator (as alſo <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>9.</hi>
               </hi> of the figure) is ſo ſtrong and well affected, both in himſelfe and his eſſentiall dignities, eleuated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the reſt, and alſo ſmall reaſon he hath, to mooue him to pronounce <q>the ruine and ouerthrow of Noble men, great perſonages and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, </q>though ſome and ſundry from time to time fall into like extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and bee ouerthrowne with the loſſe of eſtimation, goodes and lyfe, by the ſecret working of their owne pryuate natiuities, without anye generall conſtitution. But were it ſo, that <hi>Saturne</hi> (as he ſayth hee is) were diſpoſed to woorke ſtraunge feates, or to bring greate matters about: yea, and that his might were ſo much, and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice ſo great, as to ſhew the ful force of his miſchieuous and malicious nature, ſeeking to bring vpon the world, Plague, peſtilence, famine, and other calamities whatſoeuer, which haue at any tyme ſince the
<pb facs="tcp:6440:13"/> creation thereof, hapned for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſinne: yet could he not at this preſent play theſe pagea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, beeing otherwiſe brydled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned of his will, for that he is neither Lorde of the coniunction, neither hath dominion in the reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the yeare, nor ought to doe in the gouernement of the greate Orbe, or anye commertion with thoſe who haue authoritie therein. Therefore if any alteration extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary happen in the yeares fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, different from the others paſt, it muſt of neceſſitie riſe and proceed of ſome more farther cauſe, then any alleadged in al the whole Aſtrologicall diſcourſe: for as much as there is not anye one <hi>Maxime</hi> therein alleadged, that may not ſeeme. <hi>Puerile quiddam,</hi> not woorth the hazarding of any ſmall credite in Aſtrology, that hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready purchaſed (els how can one looſe that he neuer had). And for the better proofe of theſe my ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:14"/> conſider what is by him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged. <hi>Iupiter</hi> on whom ſome part of the charge is layd, ſhall begin to ſhrincke the tenth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> and goe backward, whereby his influence ſhoulde bee hindred, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing materiall. For why the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat (the coniunction I meane) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fought &amp; paſt long before, it is requiſite that the combattants doe retire and repoſe them ſelues in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray, returning backe from whence they came, which well they may do without any kind of impeachment or diſcredit in this reſpect. Beſides it is a paſſion which hapneth vnto them euery yeare once, which they can not poſſibly auoyde. Then to thinke, or bee perſwaded that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupiter,</hi> or any other of the <hi>Errones</hi> can be or ſhall be, theſe fiue or ſixe yeares next enſuing, eyther oftener retrograde then heretofore they haue beene, or than common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they vſe to bee, is moſte abſurde &amp; chieldiſh, and argueth that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:6440:14"/> is of that opinion can be but a ſimple Aſtrologian, not ſeene at all in the <hi>Theory</hi> of the Planettes, nor well acquainted with <hi>Coperni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> his <hi>Hypotheſes, Rein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olts</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, or <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbachius.</hi> Foraſmuch as it is a poſition or rule infallible that a Planet cannot paſſe by his firſt ſtation aboue once, while hee maketh his reuolution in his epici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle, &amp; by it he muſt of neceſſity once paſſe, and the <hi>tempus periodicum</hi> of his reuolution is certain, conſtant, and without alteration. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if hee euer ſee <hi>Saturne</hi> oftener retrograde, then once in twelue moneths and eighteen daies <hi>(men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſolares</hi> I mean) or <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>13.</hi> moneths and <hi>9.</hi> dayes, <hi>Mars,</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> years and <hi>2.</hi> moneths, <hi>Venus</hi> in one yeare <hi>7.</hi> monethes and <hi>14.</hi> dayes, <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>3.</hi> moneths &amp; <hi>26.</hi> dayes, or if he can find that they eſcape re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trogradation in any of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed times, then let me looſe the credite of mine Aſtrology, vnleſſe it
<pb facs="tcp:6440:15"/> pleaſe the almighty to work mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles more in theſe <hi>6.</hi> yeares follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>1600.</hi> yeres heretofore: and were his meaning no leſſe, yet were it doubtfull, whether the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the Aſtrological diſcourſe. were a <hi>conſilijs illius,</hi> and priuie to his intent. But admit it were as he ſaith, that they were oftner retro grade then in times paſt, and that which is more then ſo, that the ſun ſtood ſtil, or went backward, contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to his naturall motion: yet were it no argument thervpon to inferre the diſſolution of the world, or ende of the ſame: conſidering that in the time of <hi>Ioſua,</hi> the Sunne ſtoode ſtill: and in the tyme of <hi>Ezechias,</hi> the Sunne went backe: and the world notwithſtanding continuing after the ſpace of ſixtéene hundred yeres, and not ſo little. And whereas he alſo ſayth, that the <hi>26.</hi> day of <hi>October</hi> they are almoſt in coniunction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. I anſwere that almoſt neuer won the game, nor almoſt did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:6440:15"/> hit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nail on the head, &amp; althogh they bee in application, yet is the ſame but <hi>aplicatio auerſa,</hi> and is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented by refranation, afore they come to the full coniunction and as for their ſituation in the <hi>10.</hi> houſe, at the Sunn his entrance into <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> in the thirde part of the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomicall yeare: it cannot any way increaſe the hurt, ſith they haue no dominion in the ſaid yeare, for how can he gouerne a part, that is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the whole. And to returne to the conſtitution of the other Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nets, which are ſuppoſed to help for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward this cauſe, &amp; play their parts in this tragedy. <hi>Mars</hi> is the man moſt ſuſpected herein: who though he be <hi>peregrine,</hi> yet by his dignities coequall with his debilities, and therefore become indifferent and of a meane diſpoſition, who although he be in <hi>Leo,</hi> yet is he not in <hi>Cacode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> neither is he any way ſo gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſgraced or euil affected, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ſhoulde be thought to pretend
<pb facs="tcp:6440:16"/>
               <q>any ſuch wonderfull contention, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, treaſon, rebellion, warres, tumultes, mutines or vprores, with horrible ſlaughter and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,</q> but rather warranteth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, this his terrible prediction and fearefull prognoſtication to paſſe like a ſhaddowe, or vaniſhe like a ſmoke, not vnlike quickſiluer mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire, or as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crack of a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non charged without a bullet, only making a fearful noiſe, and cauſing no further harm.
<q>He ſaith alſo ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, that great multitudes ſhalbe ſpoiled, ſubdued, deſtroied &amp; murthe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, by the enemy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould oppreſſe them with the ſworde &amp; fire, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tragical miſcheifs &amp; notorious calamities, to be preſaged to ſome mighty ruler or gouernor, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in high dignitie or ſupreme au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</q> 
               <hi>Mars</hi> being neither in the <hi>10.</hi> nor hauing dominion therein. Furthermore, he ſuppoſing <hi>Mars</hi> to be Lord of the <hi>9.</hi> houſe, inferreth therevpon euill ſucceſſe to the clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:16"/> whereas in truth <hi>Mars</hi> hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng to doe in the ſame, neither is <hi>Mercury</hi> there vnluckily apointed, or lately of hym diſcomforted or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged with a hatefull ſquare aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect," but rather receiued with a trine into his houſe, which can by no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes" forſhewe any perſecution of the Cleargy, or any diſquiet thereby, what ſoeuer is ſignified otherwiſe. <q>Likewiſe <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>12.</hi> houſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aſcendent (as he would haue hym) can not threaten loſſe or deſtruction in thoſe kindes of beaſts that haue houes, hornes, and fleeces, nor hinder the increaſe of Waſpes, Piſmires, Caterpillers, Cormoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and vermin:</q> but that thei ſhould abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to much (if it pleaſed not God otherwiſe to hinder the ſame) who becauſe he is not ſeated in the eight houſe from the Moone, <hi>Ipſe non ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificat interfectiones &amp; infirmitates magnai in hominibus.</hi> Moreouer, the Sunne beyng not Lorde of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent, nor reſident in the <hi>10.</hi> houſe
<pb facs="tcp:6440:17"/> but Lord of the ſixt, and ſituate in the aſcendent, ſheweth that <q>he ſhould im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye his influence farre otherwiſe then to buſie hymſelf, with cauſing muche trouble, vexation or ſorrowe, to Noble men, or Honourable perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages: much leſſe to thruſt any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates out of Office, depriue them of their dignities, or place other in their roomes:</q> though ſome may feele theſe inconueniences threatened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but by ſome particular and priuate cauſe, as is before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. Likewiſe, <hi>Venus</hi> no Lady of the <hi>10.</hi> houſe, though peregrine, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>buſt, and in the <hi>2.</hi> houſe, meaneth to be no partaker with the Sunne herein, though he bee in her houſe: yet is ſhe from home, minding to viſit her olde frende <hi>Mars</hi> with a ſextile aſpecte, intending to make ſome banquett or good cheare, whereby to helpe away with the ſubſtaunce that els would ruſt, rather then to forſhewe <q>the bad eſtate not onely to Princes, but of their ſubiectes likewiſe: whiche bad
<pb facs="tcp:6440:17"/> eſtate ſaieth he, ſhall be founde in the Countries that be ſituate betweene the Eaſt and the Weſt,</q> a ſentence worthy the notyng: for it contayneth muche matter, and is moſt like to be trueſt of al his predictions: for if any ſuche thyng happen in any place of the whole worlde, he thereby hits it. For what place is there vnder the Sunne, whiche is not betweene the Eaſt and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Weſt, and if he had like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaied betweene the Northe and the South, or betweene the Earth &amp; the Sky, he ſhould haue left no place of the worlde vnconſidered: for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the twoo extremes, of either theſe three euen diſtances, not onely the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal earth, but the whole is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, and by including the whole he can not lightly miſſe a parte. And <hi>Venus,</hi> if ſhe were in the <hi>11.</hi> houſe, as ſhe is in the <hi>2.</hi> is not there weakened, or vnluckely affected, for that ſhee hath <hi>23.</hi> ſtrengthes to helpe her ſelfe withall, onely <hi>9.</hi> debilities to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted: and if it may helpe, rather ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:6440:18"/> is <hi>in optimo ſtatu, quia appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu veſpertino, &amp; velox curſu,</hi> farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from the Moone <hi>Catabiba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon:</hi> 
               <q>and therefore can not ſignifie that ſubtile diſſemblyng &amp; falſe pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng amongſt men, or want of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſounde freendſhip, or muche counterfeite and faigned amitie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curteous dealyng, falſhood, breache of frendſhip, hate, diſcord, ſtrife, diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or factions, &amp;c. Nor after <hi>Haly, Destructionem futuram in mulieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, neque preſagit leguminum cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem:</hi> 
               </q>becauſe ſhe not infortunate in the <hi>11.</hi> houſe. And as for <hi>Mercury,</hi> as he is not nere his <hi>2.</hi> ſtation by <hi>25.</hi> degrees, ſo is he not in the houſe of Religion, or long iourneyes, though peregrine in <hi>Aries,</hi> his place is in the Aſcendent, and hath not to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie muche iourneying or remouyng: for although he bee <hi>Conuertibilis &amp; mobilis,</hi> yet he is ſlowe of courſe, and therfore by that Arologicall reaſon, can not ſignifie trauellyng or iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neying. Alſo <hi>Mercury</hi> hauyng no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng
<pb facs="tcp:6440:18"/> to doe in the <hi>7.</hi> houſe, nor aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the cuſpe of the ſame, cannot inferre ſundrie greeuances, <q>violent Robberies, Spoyles, wilfull Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and cruel man ſlaughters.</q> For <hi>Mercury</hi> his influence, when he hath to doe therein, is rather to incline the euill diſpoſed to ſecrete filching, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie picking, purloining, pilferie, and pety laſſeny, then vnto forcible brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, riots, or viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Robberies. And that the ſame configuration, ſhould" cauſe irreligious, impious, obſtinate" wicked, ſtubborne, &amp; diſorderly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to abounde: the marueile were not greate, conſideryng the worlde lacketh them not at this preſent, nor hath not wanted them in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: how beit <hi>Mercury</hi> (who is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertibilis naturae)</hi> chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng himſelf into the nature and diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hym whom he moſt pertily aſpecteth, who is the Moone, in this behalf, <q>can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce no ſuche effect, no more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other kinde of infortune vnto the eſtate of Embaſſadoures, Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:19"/> Notaries, Regiſters, Clarkes, Scriueners, Mercers,</q> and thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of the learneder ſort, which is no way to bee feared, conſideryng that <hi>Mercury</hi> their Significator, is both ſtrong in himſelf, and in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Figure: and as for buſie "minded fellowes, and factious heads "wedded to their owne conceites, I haue no doubt, but that they are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wedded to their owne ſorrowes and harmes, for that the buſie man neuer wanteth woe. But to come now to the Moone, who beeyng nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther peregrine, for that ſhe is <hi>in ſuo Decano,</hi> neither in oppoſition with <hi>Venus,</hi> but ſeperating from the trine of <hi>Mars:</hi> neither ſhe beeyng Ladie of the tenth houſe, but of the ſeconde: it were againſt reaſon to thinke, that <q>ſhe ſhould in that conſtellation ſhew any heauie calamities, impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, diſturbances, tribulations,</q> thought, anguiſhe, and ſorrowe vnto the common people: ſo that in very truthe, there is not one Aphoriſme in
<pb facs="tcp:6440:19"/> the whole tract, that agreeth with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of the true Coniunction: then how is it poſſible to pronounce <hi>ex faelſis verum.</hi>
               <q>Neither is it hereby to be thought, that the Commons ſhall carrie either diſloyall, biſobedient, or rebellious hartes towardes their gouernors.</q> And though the world be wickedly giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet it is not like that any ſhould bee ſo vnfaithfull to their Prince, or vnnaturall to their Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, as to diſquiet the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth therof, vnleſſe it be ſome ſuche, whoſe ſignificatours of their Natiuities be infortunately ſituate, <hi>in ſignis odioſe obedientibus,</hi> whiche from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, as thei haue vnhappely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne their Inſurrections and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions, ſo haue thei vnfortunately proceeded, and miſerablie ended the ſame. I praie GOD with my whole harte, that all ſo mynded and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, maie come to the like ſucceſſe in the ende, as no doubte they ſhall through GOD his Iuſtice, had this Coniunction neuer been. And for
<pb facs="tcp:6440:20"/>
               <q>as muche as the Sunne, beyng <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nima Mundi,</hi> is not become <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficus,</hi> neither the Fiery triplicitie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, neither the Signe of the eleuenth and fift houſe,</q> wherein the Moone can no way bee placed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Saturne</hi> in the eight, nor Lorde of the ſixth and ſeauenth houſe, his iudgement dependyng therevppon, together with other incidentes of that Figure by hym erected, are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly (as vnneedefull) for breuitie ſake omitted, and had been here vnto "ſmall purpoſe recited, but as hee is verely perſwaded that there is no Countrey, or Nation, ſhall beholde the ſame Coniunction vnpuniſhed: ſo am I certainely aſſured, that he is greatly deceiued: and were it ſo, that it extended the force and ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof, vnto the firſt and ſecond Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate (whiche is <hi>Per Meroen Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopiae, &amp; per Syene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegipti ſub Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pico Cancri)</hi> it is no doubt farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from the <hi>8.</hi> Climate, and <hi>18.19.</hi> and <hi>20. <hi>Paralell,</hi>
               </hi> wherin this our
<pb facs="tcp:6440:20"/> Countrey lyeth, neither are <hi>Piſces, Gemini, Virgo,</hi> or <hi>Sagittary,</hi> ſignes that aſcendent, or Horoſcopicall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Countries and Cities of the whole worlde: neither <hi>Saturne</hi> or <hi>Iupiter, Dij topici omnibus gentibus:</hi> and therefore the influence of this Coniunction not to ſtretche ouer all the worlde, nor vpon al ſortes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the ſame: For the omnipotent and almightie <hi>Iehouah,</hi> who ſitteth aboue bothe Planettes and Starrie Firmament, and rules them at his wil and pleaſure, hath ordeined them as well to bee ſignes and tokens of his mercie and loue towardes vs his choſen and elected, as of his wrathe and iuſtice towarde the wicked &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom he neuer brought any iuſt ſcourge or puniſhment for their ſinnes and wickedneſſe, but he firſt called them to repentaunce, by ſome ſuche fearefull ſignes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens: if the ſame might haue pearced their obſtinate and ſtony hartes. But to come to the Author his perticuler
<pb facs="tcp:6440:21"/> Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as touching weathers, and ſuche like accidentes. Nothyng there is therin contained more praiſe worthy, then the reſte before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<q>And whereas vpon the conuent and aſſemblie of the Planettes, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penyng in the Moneth of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the yeare of our Lorde <hi>1584.</hi> in the Signe of <hi>Aries,</hi> at what tyme <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> ſhall forſake the Signe <hi>Piſces,</hi> is promiſed a Comet immediatly to enſue.</q> I plainly ſaie, it is a verie weake argument where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon to inferre ſuche a greate matter and accident by, as by the induction of Hiſtories will bee proued. In the yere of our Lorde GOD <hi>1505.</hi> in the latter ende of <hi>Iuly,</hi> there was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled the <hi>Sonne,</hi> the <hi>Moone, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> a fierie ſigne: after whiche there followed no Comet. Again, in the yere of our Lorde God <hi>1544.</hi> in the middeſt of <hi>Nouember:</hi> there was <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Sol, Venus, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curie, Luna,</hi> all conuented in <hi>Sagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6440:21"/> a fierie ſigne as the former, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whiche there followed no Comet at all. Likewiſe in the yere of our Lorde God <hi>1564.</hi> in the ende of <hi>Iune</hi> there was <hi>Saturne, Iupiter, Mars, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> aſſembled in <hi>Leo</hi> a fierie ſigne, and the firſt before mentioned: After the whiche there followed no Comette, Drought, or Heate, but rather greate floodes and inundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, increaſyng the Riuer of <hi>Thames</hi> in ſuche ſort, that it ouerflo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the marſhes, and drouned muche cattell: and alſo the ſame yere there inſued a verie cold and hard Winter in ſo muche that the riuer of <hi>Thames</hi> was froſen ouer, the like whereof hath not been ſeen at any tyme ſince nor in many yeares before. As alſo <hi>Owſe</hi> bridge at <hi>Yorke,</hi> carried awaie with the force of the Iſe at the ſame tyme: Howbeit, <hi>Leouitius</hi> promiſed a Comet, and the contrary weather, who was therein deceiued, &amp; ſo maie" other preſumyng no leſſe. And as" for the Comette, whiche appeared
<pb facs="tcp:6440:22"/>
"in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1556.</hi> in the beginnyng of <hi>March,</hi> it coulde not any way be ſignified or forſhewed by that aſſembly, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was in <hi>Aries:</hi> for that the ſaied Comett appeared before there was any more entered into <hi>Aries</hi> then three, who were <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Mars,</hi> and <hi>Venus:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may ſafely conclude, that the ſaied blazyng Starr or Comet, was no more cauſed thereby, then that whiche happened after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meeting in <hi>Leo,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere <hi>1434.</hi> or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of <hi>Charlemaine Anno domini, <hi>814.</hi>
               </hi> after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in <hi>Sagittary.</hi> Wherefore, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Comet is to be preſaged, <hi>debet ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unde peti,</hi> &amp; therfore dare I not giue any conſent, to thinke that wee ſhall haue a Comet <hi>1584.</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall concluſion, and ſlender rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. For why, I am certainely perſwaded, that they are ingendred vppon ſome other farther cauſe: for that in the yere of our Lord God <hi>1572.</hi> when there was no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe
<pb facs="tcp:6440:22"/> of Planettes in fierie ſignes, there appeared a ſtraunge Comet in the Aſteriſme of <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> towarde the North parte of the worlde, in the Moneth of <hi>October,</hi> whiche was of long continuance. And again, in the yere <hi>1580.</hi> in the moneth of <hi>Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> there appeared an other toward the Southweſt, which laſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of a fortnight, &amp; appeared very great whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as there was no meetyng of the Planettes in any of the fiery ſignes, at, or immediatly before the ſame. <q>Furthermore, it is ſaied by hym, that in the Moneth of <hi>Aprill, <hi>1584.</hi>
                  </hi> there ſhould be exceſſiue cold, and extreme heate,</q> cauſed by the Coniunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Piſces,</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Aries,</hi> whiche is a thyng very abſurd: for al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know, that two extremes do make a meane, and two contrarie cauſes the one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes the other, and they both bring forth a third: as ſcaldyng hot water, and extreme colde, doe make luke warme. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:6440:23"/>
"of the yeare <hi>1585.</hi> it is not to bee thought, that the aſſemblie in <hi>Aries,</hi> ſhould pul on the effect of a Coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that was before in <hi>Piſces,</hi> a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie ſigne, and of a contrary Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and fire &amp; water ſo hardly agreeing, as alſo, for that <hi>Tranſitus</hi> (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomers tearme it) is the leaſt of all the influences. <q>Againe, where as it is ſaied, that thei whiche haue in their Natiuities the Aſcendent, the Sunne, the two ſuperious Planets, or the Lorde of the Aſcendent or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie in <hi>Aries, Inprimis, ad choreas caelestes inuitabuntur, aliquid<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> noui molientur:</hi> and that <hi>Germany</hi> &amp; <hi>Italy,</hi> with other Countries ſubiect to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> 
               </q>ſhould beware of greeuous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, chaunces and chaunges: it is farre againſt reaſon to thinke that any Conſtellation ſhould fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewe generall calamities to whole Countries, and particular prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to priuate perſons, bothe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng vnder the gouernement of one and the ſame ſigne. As touchyng the
<pb facs="tcp:6440:23"/> continuance of the former effectes, euen as the coniectures of them are very ſlender, ſo is the text of <hi>Cardane</hi> very weake to this purpoſe:
<q>
                  <hi>Effectus durant vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad reditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt pote coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio Saturni &amp; Iouis, vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad alia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> whereby his meanyng is, that it ſhould laſt the tearme &amp; ſpace of <hi>20.</hi> yeres following, whereas it is recorded amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them of no ſmall cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite in this ſcience, that the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vpon the chaunge of a <hi>Trigon,</hi> hath been ſometimes deferred vntill the <hi>3.</hi> or <hi>4.</hi>
               </q> Coniunction followyng, which is a <hi>60.</hi> or <hi>80.</hi> yeares from the ſame, or it take effect, and hath not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted aboue <hi>7.</hi> or <hi>8.</hi> yeares in effecte. But to come to the compariſon of this Coniunction with others here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore. The Coniunction which was in <hi>Cancer</hi> in <hi>Nouember,</hi> that ſhewed the generall Deluge, called <hi>Nohae</hi> floud, had other accidents co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curring with the ſame, which did aggrauate the force thereof, as theſe. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction was in <hi>Cancer,</hi> whiche then
<pb facs="tcp:6440:24"/> likewiſe was the ſigne of the greate <hi>Orbe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saturne</hi> was then lorde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greate <hi>Orbe,</hi> and was there far worſe diſpoſed then at at this preſent, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was <hi>Tardus motu, prope ſtatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in detrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to,</hi> aſwell as <hi>Peregrine,</hi> &amp;c. &amp; being ſo many waies lorde and gouernor of the whole, and ſo diuerſly feebled and weakened, no maruell though ſo greate effecte did then followe, ſuche as the world ſhall neuer ſee again: neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lation in all reſpectes. As for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Monarchie, &amp; his beginning, which happened after a coniunction in <hi>Scorpie,</hi> (but fortie yere before the beginnyng of the fierie <hi>Trigon</hi> at the leaſte) whiche Coniunction of it ſelf could as then haue doen naught, had there not been a little before, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>Orbes,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hed of <hi>Aries, octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui orbis,</hi> beyng in longitude w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Aries noni orbis,</hi> and beginnyng as then to make a new reuolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is <hi>Res magnai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>caelo,</hi> as witneſſeth <hi>Cardane.</hi> Furthermore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great <hi>Orb</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6440:24"/> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame time was <hi>Aquarie</hi> which <hi>Orbe</hi> was as then newly begunne, and <hi>Saturn</hi> Lord of the ſayde <hi>Orbe,</hi> who did by a ſquare aſpect, beholde the ſigne of the great <hi>Orbe ex ſiguis ſe odioſe intuentibus.</hi> All which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, there is more cauſe to think that then there ſhould follow ſome notable ſubuerſion, rather then now, when as none of the like ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents do any way concur, againe it is no reaſon to thinke that the watry <hi>Trygon,</hi> which beganne the fourth Monarchy, ſhoulde likewyſe finiſh the ſame: <hi>Quia idem non po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt eſſe cauſa generationis &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis.</hi> And as touching the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was ſixe yéeres before the bleſſed and happye byrth of our ſauiour Chriſt, the which <hi>Leoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> putteth in <hi>Piſces, Cardane</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſame to be in the thyrd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of <hi>Aries,</hi> and the fiery <hi>Trygon</hi> already begun, which controuerſye of theyrs (béeing men excellentlye read and learned) I referre to my
<pb facs="tcp:6440:25"/> betters to decide. Laſtly in the time of <hi>Carolus magnus,</hi> the <hi>Trygon</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging into <hi>Aries,</hi> came as then into the ſigne of the great <hi>Orbe</hi> and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Mars.</hi> And ſith that by proceſſe of time, we are now come againe to the ende of the watry <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gon,</hi> and beginning of the fierye, it is requiſite before we ſhal preſume by Aſtrologicall coniecture, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ende and conſumation of the world, ſhoulde be in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1588.</hi> We ſhould firſte conſider whether there happen any chaunge of the greate <hi>Orbe,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the eyght and ninth <hi>Orbe,</hi> eyther els the chaunge of any <hi>Abſit</hi> out of one ſigne into an other. All which, as <hi>Cardane</hi> witneſſeth. <hi>Sunt res magnae in Coelo.</hi> If ſo bée that ther be any ſuch cauſe concurrent, then is ſomewhat to bee ſpoken thereof, otherwiſe little to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. The propheſies of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures firſte moſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced and beſte conſidered aboute
<pb facs="tcp:6440:25"/> the ſame, and then the Aſtroglio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call coniectures compared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, and carefully foreſeeing that we alleadge not, <hi>Non cauſam pro cauſa,</hi> ſome reaſonable eſtimate may bee made thereof. But the day and houre is vnknowne to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of heauen, And ſo to return to the laſt notable matter by him ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, which is, that there ſhall not appeare vnto vs in our Horizon, anie Eclipſe, of the Sun, or moone this year. But how greate or how notable a thing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidred, I leaue to thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are meanely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed in Aſtronomy. But as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the influence of the Eclipſe of the Sunne, that was in <hi>Cancer,</hi> the laſt yeare <hi>1582,</hi> whereof there is wonders promiſed, we are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine. And firſt the cauſe of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe well knowne, we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the quantitie of the Eclipſe, and the continuaunce of the ſame. <hi>Leouitius at Augusta,</hi> putteth it to be the twenteth of Iune, at foure
<pb facs="tcp:6440:26"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock, fiftie thrée minuts in the morning, and thrée poyntes ſeuen minutes darkened, and continued an houre &amp; twentie two minutes. <hi>Maestlin</hi> for <hi>Tubing,</hi> affirmeth it to be at foure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock fiftie minutes, and but two poynts foure minuts darkned, and laſted an houre and fourtéen minutes. And <hi>Stadius</hi> for <hi>Antvverp</hi> hath it at foure of the clock fourtie two minutes: But not ſo much as one ſixt part of one point darkned, nor of any continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at all, but onely a touch as it were.</p>
            <p>Wherfore if they which dwel in longitude, thirtie degrées, and haue the pole eleuated fortye eight de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, had it thrée points darkned, &amp; they in longitude thirtie one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées, vnder the eleuation of four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine degrées, had but two points darkned. Likewiſe they that dwel in longitude twentie ſix degrées vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the eleuation of fiftie one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſawe nothing at all. How
<pb facs="tcp:6440:26"/> is it poſſible that they which are in longitude nintéene degrées, vnder the eleuation of fiftie two degrées, ſhould ſée any thing. And for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſurreption of light is the grounde wherby to iudge of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents: I thought good to take the paines, to prooue by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Art, whether there were any ſurreption in our Horizon or no, with the reſt of the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therunto apertayning. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may appeare to any that is ſtudious or deſirous to come to the trueth thereof, in manner as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>die.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ho.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>mi.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Viſibilis coniunctio ſolis &amp; Lunae.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>19.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>16.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>30.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>11.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diſtantia verae coniunctionis a viſa.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>59.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Còn iunctio vera.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>19.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>17.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>30.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anomalia ſolis annua.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſex. 5.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>58.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>39.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>39.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Anomalia lunae Coaequata.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>4.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>8.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>19.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Motus verus latitudinis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>27.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>20.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diſtantia ſolis ac lunae a vertice.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>gra.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>86.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>26.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Paralaxis Lunae ad ſolem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>55.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>23</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Paralaxis Longitudinis lunae ad ſolem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>33.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>54</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Paralaxis Latitudinis lunae ad ſolem.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>46</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>47.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6440:27"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>mi</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>6</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Latitudo lunae vera.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bor.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>14.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>13.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Latitudo lunae viſa.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Auſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>32.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>16.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semidia meter ſolis viſualis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>15.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>49.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Semidia meter lunae viſualis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>16.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>53.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Congeries ſemidia metrorum.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>32.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>42.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Digiti ecliptici.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>digit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>9.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>32.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Tempus inſidentiae.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ho.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>5.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>0.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>WHereby it may euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that there was ſcant the ſixt parte of one pointe of the Sunnes body eclypſed, what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was ſeene at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whome ſo euer, vnleſſe they had their <hi>Oſſa iugalia nimium exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi> As <hi>Cornelius Gemma</hi> had, when he conſidred the Comet that was in <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> which made them ſee the thing which was not, els had they not <hi>Neruum opticum bene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> which made that ſmall darkeneſſe to appeare ſixteene tymes bigger then it was, and the obſcuration beeing but the ſixte parte of one poynt, is a thing of none account at all, as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell ſhewed. For that ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence
<pb facs="tcp:6440:27"/> that it had, began the ſixt day of Iuly, laſted two monethes, and ended the ſeuenth of Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber following in the ſame yeare. Wherefore the effectes thereof can not by any <hi>Astrologicall</hi> reaſon be deferred till May <hi>1583,</hi> and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a yeare. Thus is there ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor bad can bee aſpected from this Ecclipſe. As for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring with other Eclipſes is néedleſſe. But one example muſte not be omitted.
<q>If this Eclipſe had beene darkned three pointes as it was not (thogh he ſo ſay therof) In the yeare ſayth he, <hi>1536.</hi> the <hi>13.</hi> day of Iune, at one of the clocke after noone was an eclipſe of the Sun in the ſeuenth degree of <hi>Cancer,</hi> the ſun was darkned eight pointes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte,</q> with them at <hi>Tubing,</hi> but much leſſe with vs at <hi>London,</hi> and from the beginning to the end, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted two houres and ſixe minutes. The effectes whereof began in Ianuary following, the tenth day,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:28"/> and laſted two yeeres, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth that this Eclips could not foreſhew the two great commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that were in Lyncolneſhire and Yorkſhire, which were bothe of them begun &amp; ended in <hi>October</hi> before the influence of this eclipſe tooke place, at leaſt the ſpace of <hi>2.</hi> monethes. But for confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Art, let vs ſée what happened fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ianuary <hi>1537</hi> till Ianuary <hi>1539.</hi> when as the influence of this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe raged. In February there was ſtirred a rebellion, wherein <hi>Carlile</hi> was beſieged. In April af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ther was a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motion in Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſetſhire, about taking vp of Corne, and there was from the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginning to the ende, aboue ſixtye perſons executed and put to death for treaſon, rebellion, and denying the Kinges Supremacy: of which number there was a Marqueſſe, thrée Lordes, ſixe Knightes, thrée Abbotes and a Ladye, that was brent in <hi>Smithfield (Quiae Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis
<pb facs="tcp:6440:28"/> fuit in decima domo regis, &amp; prope locum ſolis aphetae ſuae geneſis)</hi> If we may giue credit to <hi>Cardane,</hi> al ſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time there were ſundry ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys ſuppreſſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> black Fryers, the white Fryers &amp; the Monckes of <hi>Charterhouſe,</hi> ſoone after all the reſt, <hi>(Quia in nona domo quae eſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus religionis)</hi> As for any dearth or ſcarſity, ſickneſſe or mortalitye, I reade of none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> followed, neither of inundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or flouds but great hurt by fire was done in <hi>London</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baſketmakers in <hi>Roode Lane,</hi> where twelue houſes and nine perſons were burnt in the ſpace of thrée howers, beſides frier Foreſt and other that were brent in <hi>Smithfield,</hi> and a great many of Images (for auoidi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of Idolatry) were burnt at <hi>Chelſey (Mars ferie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat gradu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eclipticu quadrato breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um)</hi> Likewiſe on a ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time, appeared at <hi>Pauls Croſse</hi> the <hi>Rood of grace,</hi> and there moued the mouth and lips, very ſtraung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.
<pb facs="tcp:6440:29"/> But it was brought thither out of <hi>Kent,</hi> and with ſundry deuiſes made ſo to doe. Afterwarde by the ſame Preacher the Biſhop of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester</hi> was ſhewed the bloud of <hi>Hales,</hi> and prooued to be no bloud, but clarified hony mixte with Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron. And laſtly, to conclude and to ſhew, that ſome good as well as ill, may be foreſhewed by an Eclipſe, as wel priuatly, as publiquely, par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticularly, as generally. Ther were (during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> influence of that Eclipſe) <hi>18.</hi> States created and aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Alſo the vertuous and Godly Prince <hi>Edward,</hi> afterwardes king <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt was borne, a great ioye to the whole Lande. Alſo the Bible in engliſh was ſet in euery Church of the Realme for all men to read: And thus much for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Aſtrologicall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and poſitions therin contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And for as much as it is not thuoght ſufficient for any one to reprehend or reprooue the doinges
<pb facs="tcp:6440:29"/> and procedinges of other writers vnleſſe after confutation of their erroure made, hee ſéemeth further to adde of his owne, ſomewhat ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more Subſtantiall in doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, reaſonabler in hearing, or with the truth of the matter bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agreeing. I haue there vppon thought it not amiſſe, to follow an order and platfourme of iudgement in the declaration hereof vſed by <hi>Ptholomy,</hi> and other learned wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of later tyme. Wherein it is firſt requiſite to vnderſtand, who at this preſent is Lorde of the great <hi>Orbe,</hi> what the ſigne of the ſame is, as alſo the degree pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionall, and the diuiſor thereof. Likewiſe the Aſcendent of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, and reuolution, and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who hath the Dominion in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunction, or preuention next and imediately going before the ſame. Al which, for the better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that which followeth, I wil breifly in order ſet down, therby y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it
<pb facs="tcp:6440:30"/> may appeare, who of theſe twaine thus conioined hath moſt force and dominion in all or moſt, of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conſiderations, for that the coniunction ſimply of it ſelfe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it hath a further conſent of the premiſſes, can not pretend or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew any great matter worthy the penning. Much leſſe the alteration of Kingdomes, the comming of Chriſte in iudgement, or conſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world. For as much as it is a matter vſually hapning once in each twentie yéer, foure times in euery ſigne, and twelue times in euery <hi>Trygon</hi> before they ſhyft, or chaunge the ſame. So that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of two hundred fourty yeares, they are twelue tymes con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyned togither, and not abooue.</p>
            <p>And what horrible matters about twentie yeares laſt paſt, in reſpect of the former reſited haue hapned, there are none of ſufficient yeares, who are not able to teſtifie. And therfore moſte ſtraunge it is, that
<pb facs="tcp:6440:30"/> the audacitie of euery ſlender ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in this ſcience, ſhould be ſuch as vpon ſo ſmall cauſes ſo certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and peremptorily, to pronounce ſuch great and wonderful effects, aſſuring the ſame vpon his credit. But how ſo euer his credit be, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine I am, that thorowe the like raſhe, and vnlearned attempts the art it ſelf, hath béen greatly diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted. In ſo much as it is in a maner contemned of the common people: the which was in times paſt eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med both of Prince and Potentate in ſuch ſort as they became earneſt Stude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts therof. Wherfore, it were to be wiſhed, that ſome of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>Mathematicians</hi> of this Age, and of this our Country wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and long experienced, would vndertake the wryting of theſe, and the like caſes, wherby other yunger Schollers might bee the more benefited, and the common wealth the better profited. And were there any cauſe of feare by
<pb facs="tcp:6440:31"/> this Coniunction portended, it were more reaſonable and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, that <hi>Liberati</hi> the <hi>Italian,</hi> ſhoulde rather admoniſh the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, then threaten the realme of <hi>England</hi> thereby. For that in the yere of our Lord <hi>1524.</hi> after the like Coniunction in <hi>Piſces,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> king was taken priſoner, at the ſiege of <hi>Paui,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon:</hi> which in diſpight of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Wolſey,</hi> went to <hi>Rome,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged the Citie, his Souldiers fact and ſpoiled it, the Pope driuen to fly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſtle of S. <hi>Angelo,</hi> wher hee continued long in calamitye. The ſeconde yeare after, was a peace concluded betweene <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> the fift yeare fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing was the newe <hi>Testament</hi> tranſlated into Engliſhe by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Tindall,</hi> and printed: the ſixt year following, the Pope was ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and ſuite to the courte of <hi>Rome</hi> forbidden, and the ſame year
<pb facs="tcp:6440:31"/> died Cardinal <hi>Wolſey,</hi> all which I am perſwaded, was no loſſe to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land,</hi> likewiſe the cleargy was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the premunire. No o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great matter happned in this land, by the ſpace of <hi>10.</hi> years after that Coniunction, except it were the loſſe of the holy mayde of <hi>Kent:</hi> who with her complices, Monkes, and Fryers, were worthely execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and put to death, and certaine houſes of obſeruaunt Friers put downe. But to return from whence I firſt digreſſed, the ſigne of the great <hi>Orbe</hi> at this preſent, is <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</hi> The Lady and gouerneſſe of the <hi>Orbe, Venus.</hi> The degree of the profection the twenty eight of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> the diuiſor <hi>Mars,</hi> the aſcendent of the coniunction, the twentie nine degree, and <hi>51.</hi> minutes of <hi>Piſces.</hi> The Lady of the hour of the ſayd coniunction <hi>Venus.</hi> The Lord and gouernour of the preuention, precéeding <hi>Venus.</hi> Al which conſide<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, it euidently appeareth that
<pb facs="tcp:6440:32"/> 
               <hi>Saturn</hi> hath no Dominion in any of the premiſes, much leſſe in al, or the moſt of them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were he <hi>Potentior Joue in loco coniunctionis,</hi> as ſome in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately haue ſuppoſed him, yet cold-he not at this preſent, work thoſe effects by him ſignified, by reaſon of his diſſent and diſagréement o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. But according as Iels where promiſed. I wil firſt begin with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> in the ſixtie three propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiloquium,</hi> whoſe words are theſe. <hi>Cum Saturnus Iupiterque co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gunter vtrum eorum ſublimior ſit vide, &amp; iuxta illius natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pronuntiato.</hi> The which propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> containeth much matter, and very difficult in few wordes. For by the word coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as ſome of the learned haue interpreted, he meaneth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place, <hi>Coniunctionem tam ſecundum latitudinem, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> longitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Both which at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by great good hap, in a maner concurre, though
<pb facs="tcp:6440:32"/> the ſame by the Aucthor bee neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and omitted. A farther conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whiche notwithſtanding of other ſome there is required here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the vniting and contactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their bodies, the whiche (for that the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their Latitudes is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Semidiameters of their bodies) can not be: for as muche as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midiameter of the bodie of <hi>Saturne</hi> is but <hi>4.</hi> minutes, and the Semidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the bodie of <hi>Iupiter</hi> is <hi>6.</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes, bothe whiche added together maketh <hi>10.</hi> minutes, and the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of their Latitudes is <hi>26.</hi> minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: Ergo, it appeareth as is ſaied: and how requiſite this third conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is in the iudgement of corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Coniunctions: ſaie thei, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Sunne and the Moone doth euidently declare. For that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the Latitude of the Moone excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Semidiameter of both their bodies, there happeneth no Eclipſe, be the Coniunction otherwiſe neuer ſo partile, the which opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> although
<pb facs="tcp:6440:33"/> it bee very reaſonable and probatle, yet will I not much ſtande therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, for that it ſeldome happeneth to concurre with the two former conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, and yet the Coniunction pretending matter to inſue: how be it it muſt of neceſſitie be graunted whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſo happeneth, to be the more ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatiue, and of greater effect <hi>Ceteris paribus.</hi> The ſecond point contained in the former propoſition, is to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this Coniunction <hi>Quis eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſuper alterum,</hi> the whiche worde <hi>eleuatio,</hi> for that it is ſomewhat am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous, is therefore diuerſly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of ſondrie Writers, ſome ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng it in one ſence and ſome in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Trapezuntius</hi> commentyng vpon the ſame propoſition vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Per eleuationem altitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netae in epiciclo,</hi> affirming that when ſoeuer two Planets are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he that is neareſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twaine vnto the <hi>Apogeon</hi> of his <hi>Epicicle, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur eleuatus ſuper alterum,</hi> &amp; when they are of like diſtaunce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:6440:33"/> 
               <hi>Apogeon: Quod nullus eleuatur ſupra alteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> And ſome there are, as <hi>Guido,</hi> and ſuch like, who referre the ſame vnto the latitudes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> planets ſo conioyned thus ſaiyng thereof, that if it happen their Latitudes to be both one way and into the North, he whoſe Latitude is greater to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuated aboue the other, but if bothe their Latitudes bee into the South, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he to be eleuated whoſe latitude is leaſt of the twaine: If the latitude of the one bee into the North, and the Latitude of the other into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> South, then he whoſe Latitude is into the North, is eleuated aboue the other in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> South: but if their Latitudes be bothe one way and like muche, then he who is aſcendent to be eleuated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the other deſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the ſame, and when as neither of them haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Latitude from the Ecliptike, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none to be eleuated aboue the other, and a third ſorte there are who conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Per eleuationem, declinationem ab Equatore:</hi> ſaiyng, that in this and
<pb facs="tcp:6440:34"/> the like Coniunctions, it is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, <hi>Quis planetarum habet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorem declinationem,</hi> whiche if they happen to bee bothe into the North, then he who hath the greateſt decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the twaine is thought to be eleuated aboue the other: but if their declination bee into the Southe, he whoſe declinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is leſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twain: but if ſo be that the declination of the one be into the North, and the decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the other into the Southe, then he who hath his declination in to the North: but if their declinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bee bothe one waie, and equidiſtaunt from the Equator, then none to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuated aboue other, and they ſeeme to yeeld this reaſon of their opinion, that he who hath the greater declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the twaine bothe beeyng into the North, hath likewiſe the greater altitude Meridian, and therefore commeth of the twaine neareſt vnto our Zenith or Verticall, the higheſt and neareſt poynt of our Countrey, but when as their declinations are
<pb facs="tcp:6440:34"/> bothe into the South, the reaſon is contrarie, for that he whoſe declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is then moſte, hath the leaſt alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude Meridian of the twaine, and when their declinations are bothe one waie and like muche, then is the altitude Meridian one and the ſame, and none commeth nearer to our Verticall then the other. A fourth ſorte likewiſe there are, and they no ſmall number, who vnderſtande <hi>Per eleuationem,</hi> the diſtaunce of a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nett from the <hi>Apogeon</hi> of his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centriciti,</hi> ſo that hee who commeth neareſt vnto the ſame, is by them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuated aboue the other, and if they bee both equidiſtaunt from the ſame, then he who is aſcendent in his <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centriciti</hi> aboue the other deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng: but if bothe aſcendyng or bothe deſcendyng and equidiſtaunt from the ſame, then none eleuated aboue other, who thinke themſelues to haue great reaſon of their opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe it is daily ſeene by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne and other Planettes, the nearer they
<pb facs="tcp:6440:35"/> come vnto the ſame, the more they are eleuated aboue the earth, and higher and further from vs. A fift ſorte there are, who vnderſtande <hi>ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> after a farre other maner, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferryng the ſame vnto the eſſentiall dignities of the Planettes, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that Planet in any Coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be eleuated aboue the other, who hath <hi>Plures dignitates in loco coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis:</hi> ſaiyng, that he in reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to haue the ſuperioritie in any ſuche caſe, who hath moſte to doe therein: alledgyng <hi>Pthol.</hi> in his thirde booke in the tracte <hi>de animae facultatibus</hi> for their warrant in this behalfe, whoſe words are theſe: <hi>Magna au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſt vis planetarum potentiorum, &amp; eleuatorum ſuper mercurium &amp; lunam,</hi> where it is euident by that whiche goeth before the ſame, as thus: <hi>Quum autem ſunt in proprijs, &amp; familiaribus locis, &amp; dignitatibus planetae gubernantes animi inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Cardane</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the ſaid tracte, affirmeth
<pb facs="tcp:6440:35"/> no leſſe. A ſixt and laſt ſorte vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande <hi>Per eleuationem altitudinem planetae ſuper Horizontem,</hi> accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that Planett to bee eleuated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the other, who is neareſt to the Meridian of the twaine: As the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in the <hi>12.</hi> houſe aboue an other in the aſcendent, and one in the <hi>11.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſame in the <hi>12.</hi> and one in the <hi>10.</hi> aboue the ſame in the <hi>11.</hi> For as much ſay thei as it is daiely ſeen, that as the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne paſſeth theſe poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and houſes, he aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth higher and higher vntill he come vnto the higheſt poynt thereof, and his heate and force in eache of the ſaied poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes more and more encreaſing, vntill he come at the full Meridian and higheſt poynt from the Horizon. And of this opinion is the learned <hi>Leonitius</hi> in his iudgement <hi>de nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatibus</hi> in the chapter <hi>de coniugio,</hi> his wordes beeyng theſe: <hi>Saturnus proxime ſupra vtrum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſignificatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem coniugij, ſtellam (lunam ac ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerem) eleuatus, ita vt nullus, pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:36"/> planeta interueniat, &amp; ex loco maxime ſublimiſz. medij coeli apice vtrunque velu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deprimens, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iugium huic nato denegat:</hi> &amp; other late Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for the better maintainyng of this opinion, alledge the aucthoritie of <hi>Pthol.</hi> in the thirde Booke in the tracte <hi>de leſionibus, &amp; morbis corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</hi> Whoſe wordes are theſe: <hi>Rur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus quando venus eſt in cardinibus dictis maxime in occid. iuncta Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, aut eum aſpiciens, aut domicilia mutarunt, Mars ſuper cum eleuatur &amp;c.</hi> And in the fourth Booke in the Chapter <hi>de facultatibus,</hi> alledgyng theſe wordes following: <hi>Conſideren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur alij fausti planetarum aſpectus ad hos &amp; illi qui eleuantur ſuper hos ex eadem vel contraria qualitate.</hi> And again in the ſame Booke in the trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te <hi>de magiſterio</hi> as followeth: <hi>&amp; cum beneficae ſtella ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t eleuati ſuper domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantes, faciunt magnos glorioſos &amp;c. Econtra cum malefici eleuantur ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per dominatores, faciunt ſubmiſſos i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnobiles, nihil lucrantes &amp;c.</hi> In all
<pb facs="tcp:6440:36"/> whiche places alledged it is euident ſay thei that the authors vnderſtand, <hi>Per eleuationem, altitudinem plane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae quoad mundum vel Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> by reaſon of whiche diuerſitie and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarietie of opinions, it is not a little difficult to determine the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation or ſuperiority of theſe twaine thus conioyned: but for as muche as the propoſition before reſited is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of <hi>Pthol</hi> I thincke it moſt reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to confirme his meaning here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by hymſelf, and the like wordes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of hym els where, takyng <hi>eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem</hi> in this place in bothe the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by hym alledged, accordyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bothe whiche it will appeare that <hi>Iupiter</hi> is <hi>Sublimior</hi> of the twaine. Firſt, for that he is in <hi>domo propria &amp; dominus coniunctionis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saturne</hi> hauyng no one dignitie therein, nor ought to doe in the ſame. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe hee is <hi>Saturno eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior quo ad mundum vel Horizon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> whereof there maie bee ſome doubt, conſideryng that thei are both
<pb facs="tcp:6440:37"/> in one degree and minute very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly conioyned, which not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng becauſe <hi>Iupiter</hi> his latitude is leaſt of the twaine, his diſtaunce therefore <hi>a Meridie</hi> muſt be leaſt of them bothe, and therfore his altitude aboue the Horizon moſt, <hi>Et ergo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limior Saturno:</hi> What then follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in the former propoſition, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xta illius naturam pronunciaeto,</hi> wher by it is manifeſt that this ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the two ſuperiour follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the influence, operation, and propertie of the moſte happy, proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and beneuolent Planette <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> whoſe influence and irradiation is not at any tyme to work hurt to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, muche leſſe when as he is ſtrong in hymſelf, well affected, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and hauyng the prorogatiue and preheminence aboue the reſt, for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at any tyme he hath the Dominion and gouernement of an Eclipſe, a matter farre more ſignificatiue then this ſeely and ſimple Coniunction, conſideryng that the ſaid <hi>Iupiter</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:6440:37"/> gouernor and diſpoſer thereof is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>dominus aſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunctionis,</hi> becauſe the aſcendent is the laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree &amp; almoſt laſt minute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne <hi>Piſces:</hi> neither <hi>dominus aſcendentis reuolutionis:</hi> neither <hi>dominus orbis magni,</hi> nor <hi>preuentionis prox. prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis.</hi> For <hi>Pthol.</hi> writing and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng the naturall cauſes of generall calamities, aſcribeth more vnto the Eclipſes then vnto any other: thus ſaying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Prima &amp; efficaciſſima taliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euentuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa, eſt copulatio ſolis &amp; lunae in defectibus:</hi> And next after Eclipſes, he affirmeth Cometts and blaſing Starres to haue a greate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and ſignification, whereof he thus teſtifieth in the <hi>28.</hi> propoſition of his <hi>Centiloquium. Tratectiones at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que crinitae ſecunda partes in Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cijs ferunt,</hi> and yet whenſoeuer this Planette <hi>Iupiter</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> haue the whole dominion in either of the ſaid places, as they haue in this Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they turne the ſignifications thereof, vnto much good proſperous
<pb facs="tcp:6440:38"/> happe and effect, as appeareth by the ſaied <hi>Pthol.</hi> Thus writyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the ſeconde Booke in his tracte <hi>de eclipſibus</hi> there inquiryng, <hi>Quales futuri ſunt euentus boni vel mali.</hi> Thus muche affirmyng of the ſaied Planette <hi>Iupiter cum ſolus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatur, increme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta efficit, cumque e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentus ad homines pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, gloriam, fertilitatem, tranquillitatem, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſignificat &amp;c.</hi> And no leſſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication hath the ſaied <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and either of them in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of Comettes and Meteors, as witneſſeth <hi>Mizaldus</hi> and others, who haue written <hi>de Cometographiae</hi> and were this not ſo, Commets and Eclipſes could not at any tyme ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and pretende good happ and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to followe and enſue: the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie whereof experience doeth teſtifie: for as muche as after the appearance of the Comette in <hi>Libra</hi> the Diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall houſe of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and vnder the beames and irradiation of the moſte proſperous and beneuolent Planett
<pb facs="tcp:6440:38"/> 
               <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the Natiuitie of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, there followed greate ioye, peace and comforte vnto the whole worlde, and what good effectes haue inſued of Eclipſes in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Countries, eache meane <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nographer</hi> is able to teſtifie. If then in ſuche greate matters as E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſes and Comettes, the force of theſe Planettes bee ſuche, vppon their dominion there, I ſee no cauſe but to hope and expect the like here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, the power and authoritie of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> being no leſſe in this Coniunction, the one <hi>quia dominus,</hi> the other <hi>quia Almute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and the ſame ſo muche the rather for that the ſaied <hi>Iupiter</hi> hath none eleuated aboue hym thereby to lett and inhibite his influence, but is both the higheſt and the ſtrongeſt in the figure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the good effectes promiſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſo muche the more, as witneſſeth <hi>Pthol.</hi> in his ſeconde Booke <hi>de pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionibus Astronomicis:</hi> His wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des being theſe: <hi>Etenim beneficae ſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6440:39"/> &amp; locis euentui obnoxijs cognatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aliqua iunctae, ſi non ſuperentur ab alijs contrariae ſectae ſtellis, efficatius quod policentur naturae ſuae bonitate abſoluunt:</hi> Wherefore it is requiſite to ſhewe and declare to whom and what Countries this ſaied good by this Coniunction promiſed is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially portended: for as muche as it were abſurde in reaſon to thincke this ſame to bee prefigured vnto the whole, or vnto theſe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame in the Exacte tyme of the Coniunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth not appeare: For as a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mett ſignifieth not but vnto thoſe to whom the ſame doeth firſt ſhewe and appeare: or an Eclipſe, but vnto ſuch as ſe and behold the ſame, their reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions notwithſtandyng about the whole within the ſpace of foure and twentie houres: the like conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therefore of this Coniunction not without cauſe at this preſent in this behalfe, accordyng to the whiche tyme and poſition it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth moſte reaſonable to thincke
<pb facs="tcp:6440:39"/> the good effectes by this Coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction promiſed and preſaged, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to touche ſuche Regions and Countreis, as lye vnder the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence thereof, and as haue the ſaid <hi>Iupiter</hi> their patron and ſignificator, as alſo vnto thoſe Countries that are ſubiect vnto the ſigne of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, or ſigne aſcendent of the ſame, or ſigne wherein the <hi>Almuten</hi> of the Coniunction is as then ſeated and placed: And for as muche as the ſigne wherein the Coniunction wil happen is knowne to be of the fourth and laſt triplicitie, it hath his ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in the Countries, liyng in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the whole Southweſt, and thoſe eſpecially of the ſame ſituate on the Sea coſte, and certaine I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes liyng in the ſaied point, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo other Countries in the like poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion inuironed with many Riuers or greate waters, and to diſcende more particularly, vnto <hi>Normandy, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall,</hi> and <hi>Compestella</hi> in <hi>Spaigne,</hi> and no leſſe good hap promiſed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:6440:40"/> vnto the Countries lying and ſituate in reſpect of vs Southeaſt, adioyning and bounding vppon the North Seas, <hi>Quia Iupiter huius bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni author &amp; ſignificator orientalis a ſole, &amp; in latitudine australi, ac in pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcibus, ſigno aqueo ac ſeptentrionali.</hi> And the ſigne <hi>Gemini</hi> wherein the <hi>Almuten</hi> of the ſaied Coniunction moueth, ſomewhat confirmeth the ſame: <hi>Habet enim ſignum geminoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ex regionibus Flandriam, Brabantiae<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. Et quia Iupiter huius rei domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator fortis eſt per ſe, &amp; erga ſolem, &amp; in domo pauoris, tristiciae, meroris, captiuorum, ac incarceratorum ſit us, ac ſupra ſaturnum eiuſdem domus dominum exaltatus, eumque de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, exilij, inopiae, angustiarum, lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, pauoris, interitus, vastitatis, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis ac penuriae dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorem maxime neceſſarioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum.</hi> What is hereby to be thought? but that the impriſoned in the ſaied places to bee releaſed, &amp; the captiues ſet at libertie, their dearth &amp; penurie
<pb facs="tcp:6440:40"/> turned into more abundance &amp; plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, their feare to ioy, their thraldome to libertie, their ſorrow to comfort, &amp; their long warre to ſodaine and ſhort peace, &amp; the ſame ſo much the rather, if other more forcible &amp; effectual cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cur with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes héereafter following, the one ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting néere vnto the degrée of the ſayd coniunction, &amp; the other not far from the degrée opoſite to the ſame, but the good before promiſed is not like pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to take effect, but after certain ſmal treſons, trecheries, ſecret conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſies, &amp; a few like troubles before going: for although <hi>Iupiter</hi> haue héer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victorie &amp; ſuperioritie, diſpoſing for the moſt part the coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction after his own inclination &amp; diſpoſition: yet can it not be denied, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Saturne</hi> worketh therin ſome little and ſmal effect, though nothing in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former good, &amp; far leſſe then otherwiſe he would, had he had the ſuperioritie and ſupremacie therein. And it may ſéeme ſomwhat ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thus to think,
<pb facs="tcp:6440:41"/> conſidering that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid <hi>Saturne</hi> is in this coniunction peregrine, weake, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out dignitie, as alſo in <hi>domo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente,</hi> a weak place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure, wher vnto I anſwere, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> 
               <hi>Haly, Abenragell,</hi> &amp; other, that although he be without dignitie, yet is he not voide of influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, as alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the <hi>malefici</hi> being pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grine, are then readier &amp; apter to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe then otherwiſe: howbeit their force &amp; abilitie, as then not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their will, as appeareth in the direction of an <hi>Aphaeta,</hi> vnto a weake &amp; peregrine <hi>Anaraeta,</hi> and although <hi>Saturne</hi> be in <hi>Cadente,</hi> yet muſt it be conſidered with al, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is <hi>in domo in qua gaudet.</hi> And therefore it is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie way to be intended, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and ſuperioritie of the one, can quite &amp; wholly extinguiſh the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence &amp; operation of the other, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſeth it to appere mild, weak, féeble, and verie remiſſe, <hi>Vt reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brae potius, quam res ipſae videantur,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> otherwiſe would appeare, <hi>In inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciori ac ſummo gradu.</hi> And for as
<pb facs="tcp:6440:41"/> much as <hi>Cardane</hi> in his firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment vpon the ſecond booke of <hi>Pthol.</hi> his quadrupartite, there ſpeaking ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the coniunction of the ſecond ſuperiour planets, <hi>Saturne</hi> &amp; <hi>Iupiter,</hi> thus ſaith of them. <hi>Hi tamen effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vt dictum eſt, ab eclipſibus augen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vel minuantur, vel etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad effectum ducuntur.</hi> And therfore I will héer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as I haue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to write of thoſe two eclipſes before mentioned) diligently conſider what conſent, or diſcent they haue with the ſame, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to yéeld my cenſure &amp; opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thereof, knowing not what ſhuld moue the author of the late Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall diſcourſe, without the conſent of anie of the former conſiderations, ſo much to aſcribe vnto the ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction, vnleſſe the remembrance of the fiftie propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Centiloquij Ptho.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words being theſe. <hi>Ne prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mittas centum &amp; decem noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coniunctiones, in his enim poſita eſt vis eorum quae fiunt in mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do, &amp; generationis &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptionis.</hi> The which words, if hée
<pb facs="tcp:6440:42"/> ſimply vnderſtand, without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſpect (as I am certainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of no leſſe), the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſée I no cauſe but that he may vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ground take no leſſe occaſion to pronounce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like meruailes &amp; miracles, vpon the coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction of the two luminaries, the Sunne &amp; the Moone, a matter happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning once euery month, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame being one of the <hi>Centum &amp; decem nouem coniunctiones</hi> there ſpecified. But for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I purpoſed not to be ouer tedious and troubleſome vnto your worſhip in this behalfe, I wil at this preſent ceaſe the further examination &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration héereof, hoping that your worſhip will accept in good part, my ſimple and true meaning héerin, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſuch time as it may pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, to indue me with a farther knowledge in this ſcience, worthie the better liking and contentation of your worſhip.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your worſhips to command, <hi>Thomas Heth.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6440:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
